Good morning 早晨 大家好
今天我們就開始一個新的sermon series
我們就會讀《創世記》
Who's read the book of Genesis before?
OK 誰在教會長大的?
OK 我也是在教會長大的
我在香港出生
但是我五歲就去了加拿大
我一樣是在華人教會長大的
叫做Logos Baptist Church Mississauga
在西側的多倫多
你在教會長大
你就好像一個泡沫
每個人都很關心你
你的信仰系統是神愛你
神創造世界
耶穌為你死
這個Christian bubble
誰覺得他是一個Christian bubble去長大的
是一個很大的分別
你在一個Christian的家庭長大
信仰系統是很不同的
跟一個Christian的家庭相比
我爸爸是牧師
其實他在下幾個星期會在中文課講到
我在一個牧師家庭長大
更加有不同的信仰
impose on me
所以我一到了大學
這個在哪裡?
這個是什麼大學?有人知道嗎?
多倫多大學U of T
我一進到多倫多大學
Oh my eyes were open
OK my eyes were open
Next slide
我一進去一個
Science或者Biology的課程
那個教授就很反對Creationism
你們學校有沒有Biology teacher很反對Creationism?
你們高中的教授可能都很反對Creationism
我們的教授是笑Creationist那些人
They are laughing at them
他們很反對Creationism
他們很強調這個世界是Evolution自己Formed itself
所以我一進大學
我看到很多不同的Beliefs
有很多Atheist
就是不相信的那些
有些Agnostic
就是不知道有沒有神
我也不在乎的
很多不同的Agnostic和Atheist
都是很反對有這個Creationism
這個Theory的
今天我們看《創世紀》
《創世紀》教我們神如何創造這個世界
How was the world formed?
我們會看三樣東西
Three major things
第一是Trinity
第二是Cosmology
第三是Humanity
OK
Trinity, Cosmology, and Humanity
首先我們會讀《創世紀》
Let's read the next passage together
(國神創造天地,地是空虛混沌)
(軟弦壓壓,神的靈魂合在水面上)
(神說要有光,就要有火)
(國神創造地是無力,有化而光芒紛紛圍)
(人馬上有了早晨,這是靠的一天)
我們今天會Compare
Genesis Chapter 1 with John Chapter 1
我們讀英文吧
John Chapter 1
In the beginning was the Word
And the Word was with God
And the Word was God
He was with God in the beginning
Through Him all things were made
Without Him nothing was made
That has been made
In Him was life
And that life was the light of all mankind
The light shines in the darkness
And the darkness has not overcome it
好,我們現在會分組五分鐘
我們Compare一下這兩個Scripture
Genesis 1 and John 1有什麼Similarity
一個很Simple的Exercise
接著第二個問題是
你怎麼看到Trinity in Creation
OK,怎麼看到三維一體創造這個世界
Five minutes, let's go
OK,我考一下這組
他們兩個都是在說Creation
OK,兩個都是在說Creation
他們有說光
你講一下哪裡有說光
第三節
神說要有光就要有光
然後John那裡就是第五節
光照著黑,我不管了
OK, what is the similarity between Genesis 1 and John 1
The first similarity
God created the world
In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth
這組有說是用道去
用說話
The word by the word
對了,那我們怎麼看到那個word
約翰一書就是說
The word was God and the word was God
在Genesis就直接是神說
Let there be light
Very good,OK
好,誰看到那個Trinity
Who wants to explain the Trinity
In Genesis, like obviously we have God
And then there's also spirit hovering over the waters
And then light is Jesus
Like let there be light
And then in John, it also says that
Because there's also God
And the word is the word spirit
The word is like the spirit
And then light shines in the darkness
OK, very good
有幾個similarity
你們已經看到了
In the beginning
兩個都是In the beginning
第一個是
About creation of the world
The second part is about
Jesus being a part of it
兩個都是用logos
Which means word,是吧
在創世紀
神是怎樣
神是He spoke
And then it was
你看看神多厲害
祂一說
祂就是了,是吧
一說就是了
有什麼人的說話你是很害怕的
以前的皇帝
一說就怎樣
你就
是吧
祂是absolute authority
以前的皇帝
是吧
所以人們以前很害怕皇帝
你不要說不好的話
或者煮的東西祂不喜歡吃
一不喜歡吃就
是吧
OK
第三個similarity
是神在那裡
In the Hebrew
創世紀是Hebrew寫的
Hebrew
The word for God is in plural form
Plural form
OK
即是怎樣
即是不是
祂是singular
He is multiple persons
OK
我們知道
三為一體
是有什麼
聖父
聖子
和聖靈
是吧
我們回去
Let's go back to John 1
這個word
是誰
It is Jesus
Jesus is the word
為什麼我們看到
因為我們看到
In verse 2
It says He
was with God
接著
我們看到
Verse 3是什麼
Through
Through Him
我們看到這個人
是masculine
OK
我們also看到
If you look at John 1 chapter 14
The word became
flesh
and made His dwelling among us
誰是
turned into flesh
and lived among us
誰
是
Jesus
不是ET
是Jesus
OK
It is Jesus
So we know
that Jesus is the word
我們一起讀
John 1 with Jesus
as the word
OK
我們一起讀
Ready
1 2 3
In the beginning was
Jesus
and Jesus was with God
and Jesus was God
He was with God in the beginning
明白嗎
It says that Jesus was present in creation
不是只是天父創造世界
是不是
耶穌在哪裡
創造世界的時候
He was present
He was active
三為一體
是一起去創造世界的
那我們看到
聖靈
聖子
我們再看聖靈
聖靈在哪裡
Where is the Holy Spirit
我們看到
Verse 2
The Spirit of God was hovering over the waters
聖靈是hovering over the waters
祂是在指導這個創造過程
所以我們看到
我們的神
Is working in unity
Working in unity
Let's look at the next slide
聖父、聖子、聖靈
They were working together in creation
他們有teamwork
他們有unity
他們有一個purpose
Unified purpose
Unified plan
and teamwork
那我們這個比較
創世紀和約翰福音
有什麼lesson看到呢
我們看到四個lesson
第一
耶穌是part of creation
He was part of the creation
我們剛才已經說了
這個creation
是有一個relational partnership
The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit
創世紀
神是講
就是了
是不是
講就是
有光
就有光
Jesus is the word
What does that mean
Jesus is the one
that fulfills the plan of God
祂是the word
神講
耶穌出來
是不是
He fulfills the plan
耶穌fulfill什麼plan呢
耶穌fulfill the redemption plan
OK
神創造世界
這個世界好無價
好無價
你做的東西
homework
有沒有
老師讚你
做得好好
It was good
是不是
但是呢
有時我們做的東西
It was not very good
是不是
可能不是合格的
但是呢
這裡呢
神創造世界
He said it was good
是不是
祂創造了land和sea
He said it was
It was good
祂創造了animal
祂就說
It was
It was good
是不是
但是呢
我們之後會看到
這個世界
It was good
但是呢
我們有罪
就污染了這個世界
We pollute this world
所以誰要來
The second word needs to come
這個word呢
是耶穌
祂就redeem我們
這個叫做recreation
好
我們看到第一樣東西
在創世紀
第一是trinity
第二呢
是cosmology
我們ready個video
Cosmology是為什麼
What is the meaning of cosmology
Cosmos
Cosmos是什麼
宇宙
是啦
Cosmology而已
為什麼
What is it mean
OK
我們看個video
In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
The earth was empty, formless, and dark.
But the Spirit of God was there.
On the first day,
God said, "Let there be light."
And God saw that the light was good.
Then He separated the light from the darkness.
God called the light "day"
and the darkness "night."
On the second day,
God said, "Let there be a space
to separate the waters of the heavens
from the waters of the earth."
God called the space "sky."
On the third day,
God said, "Let the waters beneath the sky
flow together into one place
so dry ground may appear."
God called the dry ground "land"
and the waters "seas."
And God saw that it was good.
Then God said, "Let the land sprout
with every sort of plant and tree."
And God saw that it was good.
On the fourth day,
God said, "Let lights appear in the sky
to separate the day from the night."
God made two great lights,
the sun for the day
and the moon for the night.
He also made the stars.
God set these lights in the sky
to light the earth.
And God saw that it was good.
On the fifth day,
God said, "Let the waters swarm
with fish and other life."
Let the skies be filled
with birds of every kind.
And God saw that it was good.
On the sixth day,
God said, "Let the earth
make every sort of animal."
God made all sorts of wild animals,
livestock and small animals,
each able to have babies
of the same kind.
And God saw that it was good.
Then God said,
"Let us make man in our image
to be like us."
So God created man in his own image.
He formed man
from the dust of the ground.
He breathed the breath of life into man.
And a man became alive.
Then he saw that the man
needed a helper.
So God put man into a deep sleep.
And while he slept,
God took one of the man's ribs.
Then God made a woman
from the rib
and brought her to the man.
Then God blessed them and said,
"Be fruitful and multiply.
Fill the earth and rule over it.
Rule over the fish in the sea,
the birds in the sky
and all the animals
that scurry along the ground."
Then God said,
"Look, I have given you
every plant throughout the earth
and all the fruit trees
for your food.
And I have given you
every green plant as food
for all the animals."
Then God looked over all he had made
and he saw that it was very good.
So the creation of the heavens
and the earth
and everything in them was done.
So on the seventh day,
God rested from all his work.
And God blessed the seventh day
and said it was holy.
第一天,神創造了什麼?
Let there be light.
是的,神創造了光。
第二天,神創造了什麼?
有沒有人知道?
水,是吧?
Water and sky.
分開了水和天空。
第三天,有沒有人知道?
神創造了什麼?
是的。
神創造了土地。
神創造了土地?
神創造了植物?
是的,非常好。
第四天,神創造了什麼?
是的,神創造了星星和月亮。
神創造了日月和月亮。
第五天,神創造了什麼?
神創造了什麼?
第五天,神創造了魚和鳥。
是的,鳥。
第六天,神創造了什麼?
第六天,神創造了土地和動物。
然後,神創造了什麼?
最後,神創造了人。
好的,我們很快地看一段反轉的創造故事。
如果神先創造人,那會怎樣?
第一天,Let there be Adam,那會怎樣?
他又會怎樣?
他會餓死、冷死?
可能他無法呼吸,不知道什麼會先死?
可能他看不到東西,因為是黑暗,是黑暗,是嗎?
所以,第一天創造了Adam,我不知道他會怎樣先死,是嗎?
好的,如果第一天他先創造了鳥和動物,那會怎樣?
那些魚會怎樣?
會死,他沒有地方去游泳,是嗎?
那些小鳥會怎樣?
他沒有空氣,There's no air,是嗎?
怎麼會有空氣去…
Or maybe there's not even the physics or the…
這些Elements of H2O,都沒有創造,是嗎?
如果他先創造Sun and Moon,有什麼問題?
What happens if he creates Sun and Moon first?
但是沒有光,那這些Sun and Moon有什麼作用?
沒有作用,好像有個Flashlight,但是沒有Battery,是嗎?
沒有Battery,是嗎?
他創造了Sun和Moon,但是沒有Light,那有什麼作用呢?
There's no use,是嗎?No use.
如果他先創造了Plants,那有什麼作用呢?
沒有作用,馬上會死,是嗎?
沒有Soil,沒有Water,沒有Sun,沒有Light,那他無法Grow,是嗎?
所以我們看到神創造世界是有一個Divine Plan,OK?
He has a Divine Plan.
他是Out of Chaos to Creation.
我們很快看,第一到第三天,神是Forming.
他是Forming什麼?
這個Light,這個Darkness, the Water, the Sky,OK?
Land and Sea,他是Forming這個Base,這個是Base的。
然後第四和第六天,他是Fill,Fill the Water, Fill the Land, Fill the Sky,是嗎?
有Animal,有Bird,有Fish,他是Filling的。
所以我們看到,神是From Forming to Filling,他也是在Filming,在Filming他自己做的事情,是嗎?
他是有Purposeful Provision.
他是先Form了一些東西,然後他是Fill的。
所以那些Animal,那些Bird,那些Fish,是可以有東西吃的,可以Survive的。
From Chaos to Order.
他一開始是什麼?
From Nothing, he creates something out of nothing,因為他是神,他一說就是了,是嗎?
He spoke and it was,OK?
所以那些Atheist是很有信心的。
他因為他Believe什麼?That something came out of nothing, something came out of nothing.
那麼這個Nothing是怎樣的?Nobody knows,這個Nothing是Nothing,是嗎?
How can something come out of nothing?
但是我們相信這個創造者是神,是All-Knowing, All-Powerful, right?
He is the Loving Creator,OK?
那麼最後我們看神創造Man了,We are going to see how God creates Man.
Let's look at the next passage,我們一起看。
Then God said, "Let us make man in our image, in our own likeness,
so that they may rule over the fish of the sea, and the birds of the sky,
and the livestock and all the animals, over all the creatures that move along the ground."
So God created mankind in His own image, in the image of God He created them,
male and female He created them.
所以首先我們看到神說什麼?
Let us,又是這個什麼form?
Singular or plural,這個是plural。
Let us, God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit,
這個Trinity三為一體就說我們一起去創造人,是嗎?
那麼這個人是怎樣的?
這個人是made in what likeness?
In God's likeness,OK?
所以我們會看五樣東西。
Humanity,我們看了Trinity, Cosmology,
and now we look at humanity.
神創造人在祂的,in His image.
Five things we look at,第一是什麼?
Relationship, God created us for a relationship.
神為什麼創造你?
祂想跟你有一個relationship,
God wants a relationship with us,是嗎?
神創造了這麼多東西,
is to have a relationship with you,明白嗎?
神創造了光、地、水、太陽、月亮,
all to have a relationship with you.
Tell your neighbor, God created you to have a relationship with you.
跟你的鄰居說,第二個R是Roles.
Roles,OK?
那麼God made them什麼?
Male and female.
Male and female 有不同的role,是嗎?
Male and female are equal,是嗎?
神愛男孩多於女孩,OK?
神是兩個都愛的,男和女都愛的,是equal的,
但是有distinction,OK?
We are created with distinction,different,OK?
第三是Role,我們的Role是什麼?
Go and be fruitful,right?
Go and multiply.
Go and be stewards of the earth.
Oh,sorry,我講了reproduction.
OK,第四是reproduction,
Go and multiply, be fruitful,OK?
然後第五,下個禮拜我們會看God wants us also,
created us for rest,OK?
不是單止做事的,
我們是God created us for work,
but He also created us for rest, for rest.
OK,let's invite Nathan.
Nathan is going to come up and share a story.
你回教會多久?講了多久?
我從出世回到現在。
Wow,是不是20年了?
20 years?
差不多,20 years,OK.
在這個Creation story,你學到什麼?
What is the key thing that you took away?
就是你剛剛講的那個,我們有什麼Role,
因為我們是按照神的形象去做出來的,
我們就要用,我們要去act out祂給我們的plan.
OK,that's very good.
那你覺得神的plan for you是什麼?
你怎麼,這個禮拜怎麼act out到祂的plan?
因為我上個禮拜就幫VVS,
我就看到,在小朋友那裡,
神怎樣幫他們結果,
就是幫他們be fruitful,
就是看到很多VVS畢業的人又回來幫忙,
就是很inspirational,去到看到神的plan.
Very good.
那你現在在讀什麼?
然後你覺得神的plan for your future是什麼呢?
我現在在讀一個Sports Science的東西,
但是future有點blink.
為什麼有blink?你覺得?
我打算入Physiotherapy,但是…
成績要很好才能入?
是要很好,還有也不是有一個guarantee,
有一個successful career.
OK,那有沒有backup plan?
我可能要騎騎肚,看看神怎樣跟我說。
Very good.
Well, God created the world for a relationship with you and us.
And so, if He created us, He has a plan for us.
Amen?
Amen.
好,我們給點掌聲Nathan。
所以我們今天學了三樣東西。
What are the three ologies that we learned?
第一個ology是什麼?
The first thing is trinity.
第二是cosmology.
第三是humanity.
Trinity,我們要相信神創造這個世界。
祂創造這個世界是有一個perfect plan,
是from chaos to order.
我們要相信祂。
你今天有沒有相信神創造這個世界?
Do you believe that God created the world?
第二,Do you believe in His work?
He created the world perfectly with a plan.
第三,Do we believe in His presence?
神創造了我們,是怎樣的?
He wants to have a relationship with us.
He wants to be with you.
Through Jesus Christ, we can have a perfect relationship with Him.
Let us all stand and respond in song.
Holy Father, as we go into our groups,
may you fill these groups with the Holy Spirit,
that these conversations would lead us closer towards you,
a relationship with you.
May you bless each mentor,
that you would fill them with the Holy Spirit,
that they would speak powerfully,
not through their own words,
but through you, Lord.
And through the discussion,
every student would know more about you,
and become more like you.
In Jesus' name, we pray.
Amen.